Jian Jin (金鉴)

Tel: +86 18519643859

E-mail: jianj008@gmail.com or jian.jin@ntu.edu.sg

Personal page: https://jianjin008.github.io



BIO

I am a Research Fellow in Prof. Weisi Lin's group in Alibaba-NTU Singapore Joint Research Institute, Nanyang Technological University (NTU). I received my Ph.D. degree from Beijing Jiaotong University (BJTU), supervised by Prof. Yao Zhao and Prof. Chunyu Lin. I was a Joint Ph.D. Student from Sep. 2016 to Sep. 2018 in the School of Engineering Science, Simon Fraser University (SFU), supervised by Prof. Jie Liang. I was fortunate to work closely with Prof. Ming-Ting Sun (UW), Prof. Bing Zeng (UESTC), and Prof. Ce Zhu (UESTC).

EDUCATION

- Ph.D. in School of Computer and Information Technology, Beijing Jiaotong University, P. R. China, Sep. 2014 Jun. 2019
- M.E. in School of Electrical Engineering, Taiyuan University of Science and Technology, P. R. China, Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2014
- B.E. in School of Economics and Management, Taiyuan University of Science and Technology, P. R. China, Sep. 2007 Jun. 2011

ACADEMIC RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

- Project from Alibaba, real-time communication video quality assessment, and applications, Nov. 2019 – now, Alibaba-NTU Singapore Joint Research Institute, Nanyang Technological University.
- Doctoral Graduate Research Program, image coding and digital watermarking, Oct. 2018 –
 Jun. 2019, Beijing Jiaotong University.
- Visiting Ph.D. Research, supported by China Scholarship Council (CSC) Scholarship, (1) view synthesis distortion estimation modeling for 3-D video coding, (2) machine learning-based image/video coding and (3) automatic driving technique, Sep. 2016 Sep. 2018, school of engineering science, Simon Fraser University.
- Research Assistant, working with Prof. Jie Liang, Jan. 2017 May 2018, school of engineering science, Simon Fraser University:
- Teaching Assistant for ensc424 "Multimedia Communications Engineering", working with Prof. Jie Liang, Sep. 2017 – Dec. 2017, School of Engineering Science, Simon Fraser University, Canada
- Doctoral Graduate Research Program, objects, and microcube based 3-D video coding focus on view synthesis distortion analysis, Sep. 2015 Aug. 2016, Beijing Jiaotong University.

- Doctoral Graduate Research Program, objects, and microcube based 3-D video coding focus on the theoretical study of view synthesis. Feb. 2015 Aug. 2015, Beijing Jiaotong University.
- Doctoral Graduate Research Program, image, and video coding focus on the theoretical study of image and video coding. Sep. 2014 Jan. 2015, Beijing Jiaotong University.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

- 2-D/3-D Image and Video Coding, including traditional image/video coding, depth information quantization, depth video coding, virtual view synthesizing, view synthesis distortion estimation modeling, and perceptual video coding.
- 3-D Scene Reconstruction, including image-based rendering, graph rendering, and camera calibration.
- Image/video quality assessment.
- Perceptual video coding, including JND, visual attention, HVS.
- *Deep Learning*, including basic neural networks designing, and common platforms using, such as TensorFlow, Pytorch, Keras.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

• C/C++, MATLAB, Python (Tensorflow, Pytorch), LaTeX, Windows Office.

AWARDS (latest two years)

- 2019 Excellent Doctoral Dissertation Award of Chinese Institute of Electronics (Nov. 2019, only 26 Ph.D.s, which are in the electronics domain and graduated in recent three years, selected this award in China)
- Outstanding Graduates Awards of Beijing (Jun. 2019, only 3 Ph.D. got this award in BJTU)
- Outstanding Graduates Awards of BJTU (Jun. 2019)
- President Scholarship of BJTU (Apr. 2017 the greatest honor for the graduate students at BJTU)
- Annual Best paper of Institute of Information Science, Beijing Jiao Tong University (Jan. 2017)
- The Hanergy Li Jianing Scholarship (Nov. 2016 Rank 1)
- China National Scholarship (Oct. 2016 Rank 1)
- China Scholarship Council (CSC) Scholarship (Jun. 2016)
- Excellent Paper Award of BJTU (Jun. 2016)
- Ph.D. Innovation Fund of BJTU (Dec. 2015)
- Miyoshi outstanding graduate student of BJTU (Nov. 2015)
- First-class Ph.D. academic scholarship of BJTU (Oct. 2015)

PUBLICATION LIST

[1] **Jian Jin**, Xingxing Zhang, Weisi Lin, Jie Liang, Yao Zhao, Chunyu Lin, "Layer-Oriented View Synthesis Distortion Estimation with Learned Weights", *IEEE Transactions on Image processing* (*TIP*), 2020. (*Preparing*)

- [2] **Jian Jin**, Xingxing Zhang, Weisi Lin, Jie Liang, Yao Zhao, "Depth Quantization towards Multiple Baselines View Synthesis", *IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology* (*TCSVT*), 2020. (*Preparing*).
- [3] Chao Yao, Jimin Xiao, **Jian Jin**, Xiaojuan Ban, "Edge Orientation Driven Depth Super-Resolution for View Synthesis", *International Conference on Image and Graphics (ICIG)*, 2020.
- [4] **Jian Jin**, Jie Liang, Yao Zhao, Chunyu Lin, Chao Yao, Lili Meng, "Pixel-level View Synthesis Distortion Estimation for 3-D Video Coding", *IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology (TCSVT)*, 2019. (Accepted Online)
- [5] **Jian Jin**, Jie Liang, Yao Zhao, Chunyu Lin, Chao Yao, Anhong Wang, "A Depth-Bin-Based Graphical Model for Fast View Synthesis Distortion Estimation", *IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology (TCSVT)*, 2019, 29(6): 1754 1766.
- [6] **Jian Jin**, Anhong Wang, Yao Zhao, Chunyu Lin, and Bing Zeng, "Region-aware 3D-warping for DIBR," *IEEE Transactions on Multimedia* (*TMM*), 2016, 18(6): 953-966.
- [7] **Jian Jin**, Yao Zhao, Chunyu Lin, and Anhong Wang, "An Accurate and Efficient Nonlinear Depth Quantization Scheme," 2015 Pacific Rim Conference on Multimedia—PCM (PCM 2015), Korea, pp. 390-399, Aug. 2015.
- [8] **Jian Jin**, Anhong Wang, Yao Zhao, and Chunyu Lin, "A fast region-level 3D-warping method for depth-image-based rendering", 2015 IEEE International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing (MMSP 2015), Xiamen, pp. 1-6, Oct. 2015.
- [9] Lijun Zhao, Anhong Wang, Bing Zeng, **Jian Jin**, "Scalable Coding of Depth Images with Synthesis-Guided Edge Detection," KSII Transactions on Internet and Information Systems, 2015, 9(10): 4108-4125.
- [10] Zhiwei Xing, Anhong Wang, **Jian Jin**, Yingchun Wu, "Synthesis-Aware Region-Based 3D Video Coding," 2015 Pacific Rim Conference on Multimedia—PCM (PCM 2015), Korea, pp. 400-409, Aug. 2015.

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

• Membership:

o IEEE

• Technical Program/Review Committee Member:

- National Conference on Image and Graphics (NCIG 2020)
- IEEE International Conference on Visual Communications and Image Processing (VCIP 2018)
- Asia Pacific Signal and Information Processing Association Annual Summit and Conference (APSIPA ASC 2018)

• Reviewer for:

- IEEE Transactions on Image Processing
- IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology
- IEEE Transactions on Multimedia

- Neurocomputing
- Multimedia Systems
- EURASIP Journal on Image and Video Processing
- o International Journal of Pattern Recognition and Artificial Intelligence
- o IEEE International Conference on Multimedia & Expo (ICME 2020)
- o IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS 2019)
- o IEEE International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing (MMSP 2019)
- IEEE International Conference on Visual Communications and Image Processing (VCIP 2019, 2018)
- Asia Pacific Signal and Information Processing Association Annual Summit and Conference (APSIPA ASC 2018, 2017)

RESEARCH ACCOMPLISHMENT

My research accomplishment to date includes two directions: 3-D video coding and rendering. For 3-D video coding, I focus on depth information preprocessing to achieve significant compression for depth video. Besides, I have developed the view synthesis distortion estimation algorithm to serve for the rate-distortion optimization during 3-D video coding. For 3-D video rendering, I have proposed a region-aware 3-D warping algorithm to speedup view synthesis processing.

Depth information quantization

As known, depth information exists as floating distance data, when firstly captured by the depth sensor. In view of storage and transmission, it is necessary to be quantized into several depth layers. Generally, it is mutually contradictory between the efficiency of depth quantization and the accuracy of view synthesis. Since 3D-warping rounding calculation exists during view synthesis, depth changes within a certain range will not cause different warped position. This phenomenon provides a good way to quantize depth data more efficiently. However, 3D-warping rounding calculation can also bring additional view synthesis distortion, if the warped-interval and image-resolution-interval are misaligned. Hence, to achieve efficient depth quantization without introducing additional view synthesis distortion, an accurate and efficient nonlinear-depth quantization scheme (AE-NDQ) is presented in which the alignment between warped-interval and image-resolution-interval is taken into consideration during the depth quantization. Experimental results show, compared with the efficient nonlinear-depth-quantization (E-NDQ), AE-NDQ needs almost the same bits to represent the depth layers but maintains more accurate on view synthesis. For the traditional 8-bits nonlinear-depth-quantization (NDQ), AE-NDQ needs less bits to represent the depth layers, while has the same accuracy of the synthesized view.

Depth-bin-based graphical model for fast view synthesis distortion estimation

During 3-D video communication, transmission errors such as packet loss could happen to the texture and depth sequences. View synthesis distortion will be generated when these sequences are used to synthesize virtual views according to the depth-image-based rendering method. Depth-value-based graphical model (DVGM) has been employed to achieve the accurate packet-loss-caused view synthesis distortion estimation (VSDE). However, the DVGM models the complicated view synthesis

processes at depth-value level, which costs too much computation and is difficult to be applied in practice. In this work, a depth-bin-based graphical model (DBGM) is developed where the complicated view synthesis processes are modeled at depth-bin level so that it can be used for the fast VSDE with 1-D parallel camera configuration. To this end, several depth values are fused into one depth bin, and a depth-bin-oriented rule is developed to handle the warping competition process. Then, the properties of depth bin are analyzed and utilized to form the DBGM. Finally, a conversion algorithm is developed to convert the per-pixel input depth value probability distribution into the depth-bin format. Experimental results verify that our proposed method is 8 to 32 times faster and requires 17% to 60% less memory than the DVGM, with exactly the same accuracy.

In this work, the main contributions are listed as follows.

- The concept of depth bin is firstly defined. At the same time, a depth-bin-oriented warping competition rule is developed.
- The DBGM is developed, which is the first work to formulate the complicated view synthesis process at depth bin level to simplify the VSDE.
- The properties of depth bin are studied and utilized to optimize the DBGM further.
- A conversion of probability distribution between depth bin and depth value is developed so that it can be used to integrate the RODE method into the DBGM directly.

Pixel-level view synthesis distortion estimation for 3-D video coding

Recently, region-based 3-D video coding has been proposed. However, existing view synthesis distortion estimation (VSDE) methods are performed at the frame level. To guide the rate-distortion optimization process of region-based 3-D video coding schemes, we propose the first pixel-level VSDE (PL-VSDE) method. We first give the definition of the pixel-level view synthesis distortion. To estimate it, a backward prediction method is then developed, which starts from the pixels of interest (POIs) in the virtual view and finds their corresponding pixels in the reference view via a coarse-to-fine approach, denoted as coarse-to-fine backward prediction (CFBP) method. Additionally, the CFBP fully considers the details of 3-D warping, the rounding operation and the warping competition in view synthesis, leading to improved accuracy of the prediction. Besides, a table-lookup method and a warping property are introduced to speed up the CFBP. After integrating the CFBP into the PL-VSDE, we can estimate the view synthesis distortion at the pixel level. Our method is carried out pixel-by-pixel independently, which is friendly for parallel processing. Experimental results demonstrate that our proposed method has significant advantages in both accuracy and efficiency compared with state-of-the-art frame level VSDE methods.

The main contributions of the paper are listed as follows:

We carefully analyze the depth-change-caused view synthesis distortion, which shows that
the accuracies of the traditional depth-change-caused VSDE algorithms are not satisfactory,
since they only use 3-D warping to roughly propagate the depth-change-caused distortion
from reference view to the warped view. To improve their accuracies, both the rounding
operation and warping competition should be considered as well.

- We propose a pixel-level view synthesis distortion estimation method (PL-VSDE) to better serve the emerging region-based 3-D video coding schemes. Our method is based on a backward prediction, which starts from a pixel in the virtual view, and find its corresponding pixel in the reference view via a coarse-to-fine approach. Besides, it also considers the details in 3-D warping, rounding operation, and warping competition.
- We use a table-lookup method and the warping property to further speed up the CFBP. Besides, our method can be implemented pixel-by-pixel independently, which is friendly for parallel processing.

Region-aware 3-D warping for DIBR

In 3-D video (3DV) applications, depth-image-based rendering (DIBR) has been widely employed to synthesize virtual views. However, this approach is performed in a frame-based way, meaning each whole frame is dealt with and the characteristics of different regions in the frame are ignored. As a result, redundant pixels in some regions are abused during the subsequent warping and blending stage. We propose a region-aware 3-D warping approach for DIBR in which warped frames are reasonably divided beforehand so that only the indispensable regions are used. With the proposed scheme, it is possible to avoid noneffective and repeated pixels during the warping stage. In addition, the blending process is also saved. The experimental results show that compared to the state-of-theart VSRS3.5 and VSRS-1D-fast algorithms, our approach can achieve significant computation savings without sacrificing synthesis quality.